hi everybody welcome back to the channel
and we are doing this video from an
Airbnb in Calgary we have actually moved
over here uh what three weeks ago now
um we're doing a couple of airbnbs until
we settle into our final home if you can
hear a humming in the background it is
the fridge in this house it's incredibly
loud uh it's a bit knackered you know
but hey it's not our house so today's
video is going to be all about xanthan
gum
how you use it in your ice cream what it
is
and how it's made
so let's just get on and talk about it
[Music]
so what exactly is xantham gun well it's
a polysaccharide which is a carbohydrate
that is fermented using another
carbohydrate Source either corn or soy
or something like that and it goes
through a whole process where it
produces a barrier very much like a goo
or a slime
and when that goo or slime it has a
technical name which we'll go through in
a minute when that is worked in the
factories it gets dried and turned into
a powder that's xanthan gum so
what is the fermentation process
so the fermentation process of the
production of xanthan gum is the use of
a bacteria called xanthamona campestry
and so in the fermentation process of
the xanthamonic And Pastry it is fed
with another carbohydrate Source like I
said corn soy or wheat and that
separates the sugar into the likes of
glucose and mannose now after that
happens there is a like I've described
it before as a goo or a slime it's
actually called a polysaccharide capsule
and that is a protection over the whole
the whole fermentation process so that
it doesn't go off or get affected by
other other outside sources now once the
fermentation process is complete that
capsule that fermentation capsule is
treated with alcohol and that kills off
the excess bacteria
what you're then left with is an inert
gel
that is then dried out and then crushed
and refined into a plain white powder
that we know as xanthan gum there may be
slightly different methods to produce
xantham gum depending on the company
that makes it or the country that
they're in but by and large this process
of fermentation
heating to kill the excess bacteria
drying treating with alcohol and
cleaning and then turning into a powder
is the basic process all around the
world
[Music]
xanthan gum thankfully is a very common
additive all around the world so it's
been subjected to a lot of testing both
in North America Europe pretty much
everywhere you can buy it's been tested
within in within an inch of its life so
it has been deemed safe to use it is in
everything it is in obviously
commercially available ice creams it's
available in sauces cooking
Liquors it's in mayonnaise and ketchup
and you name it it's in everything but
not just Foods it's also in commercial
paints used as thickeners it's used in
engineering cycles for what's called Mud
which is a liquid used when drilling or
working with metals to reduce the Heat
and friction it's used in there it's
used basically everywhere so if you're
afraid of using xanthan gum then you
shouldn't be because I pretty much
guarantee you've had it somewhere your
life something that you've eaten has had
it in and the use of it in ice cream is
a really good way to make sure that all
that time and effort you've spent at
home with your ice cream machine your
results lasts much longer in the freezer
so let's talk about how we use it in ice
cream
[Music]
xanthan gum in ice cream is one of those
stabilizers that you kind of have to be
a bit careful with because it's quite
strong it's quite a powerful stabilizer
and by powerful I mean that it doesn't
take a lot to thicken up your base so
there are other type of stabilizers that
need to be heated up to certain
temperatures some are 65 Centigrade
somewhere 75 some are 90 depending on
what they are
xanthan gum doesn't need that so really
what it needs is to be gently combined
with some sugars before adding it into
your ice cream base now I would
recommend adding it in a cooler stage of
production
if you add it into your base while it's
on the hob it will thicken very very
quickly
and if you're not careful it will over
thicken your base and your resulting ice
cream once churned and Frozen will be
slightly slimy to The Taste and that's
not kind of pleasant so how much do we
need to use in our ice cream so as with
most stabilizers it's recommended to
start with 0.1 of your base mixture and
by that it means you need some small
scales to measure such light amounts
it's very difficult to take a teaspoon
or something like that and measure out
your stabilizer because you just won't
get an accurate amount now another
benefit of xanthan gum is it is a
stabilizer it is also used as an
emulsifier and it also AIDS mouth feel
or Texture for your ice cream so it's a
good General stabilizer to use if you
don't want to go to town and buy
different types of carrageenan and guar
gums you know etc etc if you want to
start with stabilizing your ice cream
xanthan gum is a really good place to do
so
so once you've added your xanthan gum
into your ice cream base you can leave
it to cool down as you would do normally
whether you do that over an ice bath
Bowl situation or you put it in the
fridge to chill down for a few hours the
choice is yours then you can churn your
ice cream as normal and what you will
notice if you do a comparison side by
side is that the stabilized version will
come to texture a little bit quicker and
then when you put it in the freezer it
actually freezes much more appropriately
with less Ice Crystal formation as well
which is one of the biggest bonuses for
using stabilizers in your homemade ice
cream
good
now finally I just want to talk about
some people's fear of stabilizers
because they're made in Labs everything
we eat is you know not everything
obviously but a lot of the products we
are made in labs and factories you know
if it comes out of a packet it's come
from a lab or a factory this is no
different it's a specific way of
producing something so if you're vegan
then doesn't mean all your products are
straight out the ground it means that
your products are treated in certain
ways and that's the same with this this
product is made for specific reasons and
uses in culinary arts so there's really
nothing to fear but I will say some
people have a reaction to xanthan gum
much like they have a reaction to any
other type of food or anything in life
to be fair you could have a reaction to
pollen
but you're not gonna stop going outside
you you would just you know work with
that allergy same with foods you can be
literally allergic to anything and it
doesn't make that food product bad for
you just means that you personally can't
deal with it your body can't process it
so if you for some reason you feel that
xanthan gum isn't for you and you are
having a mild reaction such as bloating
or IBS symptoms then maybe try a
different stabilizer until you find one
that suits you
well that's it for xanthan gum it's a
nice easy place to start it's a nice
stabilizer it's cheap to buy you can buy
it pretty much anywhere Amazon is a
great source loads of different people
sell it as well make sure you buy it
from a reputable seller because there's
lots of people selling random stuff
online these days but we'll talk about
xanthan gum again in one of our ice
cream videos and we'll start to link
some of these products up so you can
actually see and understand a bit more
about the result as we go forward so
hopefully you enjoyed our first solo
stabilizer video we're going to go
through all of them over time as I said
this is an Airbnb our new ice cream
machine has been ordered unfortunately
the company have just told me that it's
going to be delayed which is not ideal
but it is what it is
So within the next couple of months
we're going to be skit churning making
some new flavors of ice cream
we've got another Airbnb to stay in I'll
show you that when we move in there in a
couple of weeks and then after that
we'll just get making ice cream as we
did before so thank you all for
listening if you've got this far in this
video and we look forward to seeing you
next time take care
foreign
[Music]